<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A remonstrance presented to His Maiestie by the Parliament in June, ann. dom. 1628, 3 ̊Caroli Regis vvherein is discovered the great danger that England and Ireland lay under, and the Parliaments care to have secured them : as also the names of some of the enemies of the state, as Dr. Laud, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 27KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B22230</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13071682</idno>
  <idno type="VID">197877</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240853931</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing E2229</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">13071682</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B22230)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 197877)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 265:E239, no 13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A remonstrance presented to His Maiestie by the Parliament in June, ann. dom. 1628, 3 ̊Caroli Regis vvherein is discovered the great danger that England and Ireland lay under, and the Parliaments care to have secured them : as also the names of some of the enemies of the state, as Dr. Laud, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Another issue has imprint: London : Printed by T. P. and M. S. for John Owen, Septemb. 2. 1642.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Laud, William, 1573-1645.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Sources.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="petition">
            <pb facs="tcp:197877:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:197877:1"/>
            <head>A REMONSTRANCE PRESENTED TO HIS MAIESTIE by the PARLIAMENT in <hi>June, Ann. Dom.</hi> 1628. 3<seg rend="sup">o</seg>. <hi>Caroli Regis.</hi> VVherein is discovered, the great danger that <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> lay under; and the <hi>Parliaments</hi> care to have secured them. As also the names of some of the Enemies of the State, as Dr. <hi>Laud,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Most dread Soveraign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S with all humble thankfulnesse we your dutifull <hi>Commons</hi> in Parliament assembled, do acknowledge the great comfort we have in the assurance of your Majesties pious and gracious dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions; So we think it a most necessary duty (being called by your Majestie to consult and advise of the great and urgent affairs of this Church and Common-wealth, finding them at this time in apparant danger of destruction) faithfully and dutifully to inform your Majestie thereof: and with bleeding hearts and bended knees to crave such speedie redresse therein, as to your wisdom (unto which we humbly sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our selves and our desires, shall seem meet and convenient.</p>
            <p>What by the multitude and potency of your Majesties enemies abroad, what by their malicious and ambitious ends and how vigilant and constantly indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strious they are in pursuing the same, is well known unto your Majestie, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the dangers threatned thereby to your sacred person and your King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, and the calamity which hath already fallen, and daily hath increased upon your friends and Alleys, of all which we are well assured your Majestie is most sensible, and will accordingly in your own great wisdom, and with the gravest and most mature Counsell and exegency of the times and occasions, provide by all good means to prevent and help the same. To which end we most humbly entreat your Majestie:</p>
            <p>First, and especially to cast your eyes upon the miserable condition of this your own Kingdom of late so strangely weakned, impoverished and rejected; that unlesse through your Majesties most gracious wisdom, goodnesse, and justice, it be speedily raised to a better condition, it is in no little danger to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a sudden prey to the enemies thereof; and of the most happy and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishing,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:197877:2"/> to be the most miserable and contemptible Nation in the world. In the discovery of which dangers, mischiefs and inconveniences being upon us, we do freely protest that it is far from our thoughts to lay the least imputation upon your Majesties sacred person, or the least scandall upon your govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: for we do in all sincerity, and with joyfulnesse of our hearts, not onely for our selves, but in the name of all the Commons of the Realm whom we represent, ascribe as much honour to your Majestie, and acknowledgement of dutie, as a most loyall and affectionate people can give to the best King; for so you are, and so you have been pleased abundantly to expresse your self this present Parliament by your Majesties clear and satisfactory Answer to our Petition of Right; for which our selves and our posterities shal blesse God, and ever preserve a thankfull memory of your great goodnesse and justice therein. And we do hereby beleeve, that all or most of these things which we shall now present unto your Majestie, are either altogether unknown to you, or else by some of your Majesties Ministers offered under such specious pretences as may hide their own bad intentions and ill consequence of them from your Majestie. But we assure our selves, that according to the good example of your noble predecessors, nothing can make your Majestie, being a wise and judicious Prince, and above all things desirous of the welfare of your people, more in love with Parliaments than this which is one of the principall ends of calling them, that therein you may be truly enformed of the state of seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parts of your Kingdom, and how your Officers and Ministers do behave themselves in the discharge of the trust reposed in them by your Majestie; which is scarce possible to be made known unto you but in Parliament, as was declared by your blessed Father when he was pleased to put the <hi>Commons</hi> in Parliament assembled in mind, that it would be greatest unfaithfulnesse and breach of dutie to his Majestie, and of the trust committed to them by their Countrey that could be, if in setting forth the grievances of the people, and conditions of all the parts of this Kingdom, and whence they came, they did not deal clearly with him, without sparing any, how dear and neer soever they were unto him, if they were dangerous or hurtfull to the Common-wealth. In confidence therefore of your Majesties most ready and gracious acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in a matter of so high importance, in faithfull discharge of our duties we do; First of all, most humbly beseech your Majestie to take notice, that howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we know that your Majestie doth with your soul abhorre that any such thing should be imagined or attempted, yet there is a generall fear conceived in your people of some secret working and combination to introduce into this your Kingdom Innovation, and change of our Religion is more precious to us than that our lives and whatsoever this world can afford. Our fears and jealousies herein are not meerly conjecturall, but arising out of such certain and visible effects, as may demonstrate a true and reall cause. For notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing the many good and wholesome Laws made to prevent the encrease of Poperie within this Kingdom, and notwithstanding your Majesties most gracious and satisfactory Answer to the Petition of both Houses in that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half presented to your Majestie at <hi>Oxon.</hi> we find there hath followed no good
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:197877:2"/> execution or effect. But on the contrary (at which your Majestie out of quick sence of your own religious and pious heart cannot but be in the highest mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure displeased) those of that religion do find extraordinarie favours and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spects in Court from persons of great qualitie and power there, unto whom <note place="margin">Countesse of <hi>Buck.</hi>
               </note> they continually resort; And in particular is the Countesse of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> who, her self openly professing that religion, is a known favourer and sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter of them that do the same; which we well hoped upon your Majesties Answer to the aforesaid Petition at <hi>Oxon.</hi> should not have been permitted. <note place="margin">Petition at <hi>Oxon.</hi>
               </note> Nor that any of your Majesties Subjects of that religion, or justly to be sus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spected, should be entertain'd into your Majesties service, or of your royall Consort the Queen: Some likewise of that religion have had Honors, Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces <note place="margin">Papists placed in authority. Letters for stay of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists. Composi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with Recusants Inhibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Tolerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous.</note> and places of Command and Authority lately conferred: But that which striketh the greatest terrors into the heares of your loyall Subjects concerning this point, is, the letters for stay of legall proceeding against them have been procured from your Majestie (by what indirect means we know not &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>missions under the great Seal granted and executed for composition to be made with Popish Recusants. Inhibitions also and restraints both to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clesiasticall and temporall Courts and Officers to intermeddle with them: which is conceived to amount to no lesse than a toleration, odious to God, full of dishonour, and great scandall and grief to your people, and of the appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent danger of the present estate of your Majestie, and of this Kingdom. And in especiall, about <hi>London</hi> and the Suburbs thereof, where exceeding many families of them do make their aboad: A frequent Masse at Denmark House and other places; and by their often meetings and conferences, have unhappy opportunities of combining their counsels and strength together, to the hazard of your Majesties safetie and the State: and most especially in these doubtfull and calamitous times. But as our fear concerning change and subversion of Religion, is grounded upon the daily increase of Papists, the open and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fessed enemies thereof, for the reasons formerly mentioned: So are the hearts of your Subjects no lesse perplexed, then with sorrow they behold the daily growth and spreading of the faction of <hi>Arminians,</hi> (that being as your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie <note place="margin">Armini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans.</note> well knows) a cunning way to bring in Poperie, the professors of these opinions the common disturbers of the Protestant Churches, and incendiaries of those states wherein they have gotten any head, being Protestants in shew, and Jesuites in opinion and practise, which caused your royall Father with so much pious wisdom and ardent zeal, to endeavour the suppressing of them, as well at home, as in the neighbour Countreys. And your gracious Majestie (imitating his most worthy example) hath openly by your Proclamation de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared your mislike of these persons, and of their opinions, who notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing are much favoured and advanced, not wanting even of the Clergie neer to your Majestie, by name D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Neile</hi> Bishop of Winchester, and D<seg rend="sup">r</seg>
               <hi>Laud</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop <note place="margin">Dr <hi>Neile.</hi> Dr <hi>Laud.</hi>
               </note> of Bath and Wells, who are justly suspected to be unsound in their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion that way. And it being now generally the way to preferment and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion in the Church, many Scholars do bend their studies to maintain those errors: their books and opinions are suffered to be printed and published; And
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:197877:3"/> on the other side, the suppression of such as are written against them, and in the defence of the Orthodox Religion are hindred and prohibited: And which is boldnesse almost incredible, this restraint of orthodox books is made under colour of your Majesties formerly mentioned Proclamation, the intent and meaning whereof, we know was quite contrary. And further to increase our fears concerning Innovation in Religion, we find that there hath been no small labouring to remove that which is the most powerfull means to streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and increase our own Religion, and to oppose the contrary, which is diligent teaching and instructing the people in the true knowledge and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship of Almightie God, and therefore means have been sought out to depose and discountenance pious, painfull, and orthodox Preachers: and how con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable soever. and peaceable in their disposition and carriage they be, yet the preferment of such is opposed; and instead of being encouraged, they are molested by vexatious courses, and pursuits, and hardly admitted to lecture even in those places where are no constant preaching Ministers, whereby many of your good people (whose souls in this case we beseech your Majesty to commiserate) are kept in ignorance, and are apt to be easily seduced to er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and superstition. It doth not a little also increase our dangers and fears <note place="margin">Ireland.</note> this way, to understand the miserable condition of your Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> where without controull the Popish religion is openly professed and practised <note place="margin">Nunne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and superstiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous houses</note> in every part thereof, Popish jurisdiction being generally exercised and avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Monasteries, Nunneries and other superstitious houses newly erected, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edified and replenished with men and women of severall Orders, and in a plentifull manner maintained in <hi>Dublin,</hi> and most of the great Towns, and divers other places of the Kingdom, which of what ill consequence it may prove (if not seasonably represt) we leave to your Majesties wisdom to judge: but most humblie beseech you (as we assure our selves) to lay your serious consideration thereof, to your royall and pious heart, and that some timely course may be taken for redresse therein. And now if to all these your Majestie will be pleased to adde the consideration of the circumstance of time, wherein these courses tending to the destruction of true Religion within these King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, have been taken even at such time, when the same is with open force and violence persecuted in other Countreys, and all the reformed Churches of Christendome either depressed or miserably distressed, we do humblie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to your Majesties princely judgement, whether there be not a just ground of fear, that there is some secret and strange cooperating there with the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Religion abroad for the utter extirpation thereof; and whether if it be not speedily redrest, and the profession of true Religion more encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, we can expect any other but miserie and ruine speedily to fall upon us, especially if besides the visible and apparant dangers wherewith we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>passed round about, you would be pleased piously to remember the displeasure of Almightie God alwayes bent against the neglect of this holy Religion; the strokes of whose divine justice we have already felt, and do still feel with smart and sorrow ingreat measure: And beside this fear of innovation in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, we do in like faithfull discharge of our duties most humblie declare to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:197877:3"/> your Majestie, that the hearts of your people are full of fear of innovation and change in government, and accordingly possest with great grief and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row; Yet in this point by your Majesties late Answer to our Petition of Right touching our Liberties, much comforted, and raised again, out of that fullen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse <note place="margin">Petition of Right. Loan.</note> and discontent which they generally had conceived throughout the whole Kingdom, all the undue courles which were the last yeer taken for ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing of money by Loans, then which (what ever your Majestie hath been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the contrary) there was never any money demanded or paid with greater grief and generall dislike of all your faithfull Subjects; though many partly out of fear, and partly out of other respects, yet most unwillingly, were drawn to yeeld to what was then required.</p>
            <p>The billiting of Souldiers did much augment both our fears and our griefs, <note place="margin">Billiting of Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</note> wherein likewise they find much comfort, upon your late gracious Answer to the Petition of Right, and lo that which we presented to your Majestie concerning that particular, yet we humblie beseech your Majestie that we may enform you, that the still continuance and late re-inforcing of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of those Souldiers, the condition of their persons, many of them not being natives of this Kingdom, nor of the same, but somewhat of an opposite reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, the placing of them beneath the Sea-coasts; where making head amongst themselves, they may unite with a Papist partie at home (if occasion serve) or joyn with an invading Enemie to do extream mischief: and that they are not yet imployed nor dismissed, doth still minister cause of jealousie to your loving Subjects, and cannot be continued without exceeding great danger, of the peace and safetie of your Kingdom. The report of the strange and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous purpose of bringing in the <hi>Germaine</hi> horse and Riders would have tumed our doubts into dispairs, and our fears into certainty of confusion, had not your Majesties gracious Message (for which we give you humble thanks) comforted us with the assurance of your royall word, that they neither are, nor ever were intended by your Majestie for any service in <hi>England,</hi> but they were designed for some forraign employment; yet the sight of the Privie Seal by which (it seemeth) they were to be leavied for this place; the great summe of money which upon examination had been made over for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose; that much about the same time there was a Commission under the great Seal granted to the Lords and others of your Privie Councell to consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, as of other wayes of raising of moneys, so particularly by imposition, gives us just cause of suspect, that whatsoever was your Majesties own gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious intention, yet there wanted not those that under some colourable pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence might secretly by this, as by other wayes, contrive to change both the form of Religion and government, and thereby to undermine the safetie both of your Majestie and of your Kingdom: Such men could not be ignorant, that the bringing in of strangers for aid hath been alwayes pernicious to any State where they have been admitted, but to <hi>England</hi> fatall. We do blesse God that hath given to your Majestie a wise and understanding heart, to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scern the mischief of such courses, and that such power produces nothing but weaknesse and calamitie. And we beseech your Majestie to pardon the vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:197877:4"/> of our expressions, which in loyall and zealous affections we bear to your Majestie and your service; We are bold to declare to your Majestie and the whole world, that we hold it far beneath the heart of any <hi>English</hi> man to think that this victorious Nation should now stand in need of <hi>Germaine</hi> Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to defend their own King and Kingdom. But when we consider the courses formerly mentioned concerning the undermining of Religion, and those things tending to an apparant change of government; the often breaches <note place="margin">Often breaches of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Tunnage &amp; Poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage.</note> of Parliaments, whereby you have been deprived of the faithfull Counsels and free aids of your people. The taking of Tonnage and Poundage without any grant thereof by Act of Parliament ever since the beginning of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesties reign. The standing Commission granted to the Duke of <hi>Buckingham;</hi> And in time of peace the displacing of faithfull Officers and Ministers, some from Judiciall place, and others from the Offices and Authorities which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly they held in the Common-wealth; we cannot but at the sight of such approaching desolations as must necessarily follow these courses, even out of the depth of sorrow lift up our cries to heaven for help, and next under God, humble our selves to your sacred Majestie, and falling down at your feet to beseech you to hearken to the voice of all your people, which if you could hear so many thousands speaking together, they would all joyntly implore help and reformation. And if yet your Majestie will be pleased to take a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent view of the present estate of your Realm, we do humbly pray you to consider whether the miserable disasters and ill successe that hath accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied <note place="margin">Cales. Isle of Ree. Rochel.</note> all your late designes and actions; particularly those of <hi>Cales,</hi> the <hi>Isle of Ree,</hi> and the last expedition to <hi>Rochell,</hi> hath not wasted all that stock of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that was left unto this Kingdom, sometime terrible to all other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and now declining to a contempt beneath the meanest with our Honour there lost, and that not a few who had they lived, we might have had some better hope of recovering it again; our valiant and expert Collonels, Captains and Commanders, and many thousand common Souldiers and Marriners, though we have some cause to think that your Majestie is not rightly inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed thereof, and that of some thousands of your Subjects lost in the <hi>Isle of Ree,</hi> your Majestie received Information but of some few hundreds; and all that dishonour and losse hath been purchased with the consumption of a Million of treasure.</p>
            <p>Many of your Forts exceeding weak and decayed, and want both men and munition; and here we cannot but with grief consider and complain of a <note place="margin">4. and 5. Head.</note> strange improvidence, your Majestie will rather call it treacherie, that your store of powder which by order of your Privie Councell dated the tenth of <note place="margin">Powder. 10. of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> 1626.</note> December, 1626. should be constantly 300. lasts, besides a continuall supply of 20. lasts a moneth of ordinarie, and were now fit as we conceive to be doubled: that proportion which is at this time in the Tower, the present wants being served, is but nine Lasts and 40. l. in all, which we tremble to think of, and that notwithstanding this great scarsitie of powder, great quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tities should be permitted to be sold out of your Majesties store to particular persons for private gains, whereof we have seen a Certificate of 36 Lasts sold
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:197877:4"/> since the fourth of Januarie last, and your Majesties store being unfurnished of powder, which by a Contract made by Master <hi>Eveling</hi> ought to be supplied monethly with 20 Lasts, at the rate of 3 l. 10 s. 10 d. the Barrell; your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie hath been forced to pay above 7 l. a Barrell, for powder to be brought in from beyond the Seas: For which purpose 12400 l. was imprest to Mr <hi>Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamache</hi> the last yeer, and that powder not so good as that which by contract your Majestie should have of your own by one third part; all which are most strange and dangerous abuses.</p>
            <p>But what povertie, weaknesse and miserie your Kingdom is now grown <note place="margin">6. and 7. Heads.</note> into by decay of trade, by destruction and losse of ships and Marriners within these three yeers last past, we are almost afraid to declare: And could we have been sure that your Majestie should any other way have had a true informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion thereof, we should have been doubtfull to have made our weaknesse and extremitie of misfortune to appear: But the importunate and most pitifull complaints from all the parts of the Kingdom neer adjoyning to the Seas in this Land, would rend (we think) the stoniest heart in the world with sorrow, and the sence we have of the miserable condition of your Kingdom is no by-reason thereof, especially for that we see no present possible means, being now shortly to end this Sessions, how to help the same; adde such a weight of grief to our sad thoughts, as we have no words to expresse it. For your Majesties most exact information herein, we beseech you to be pleased to prove the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lender of particulars with this Remonstrance which we now most humblie present unto your Majestie.</p>
            <p>One reason of this decay of Trade, and losse of ships and Marriners, is the not guarding of the Seas; the Regality whereof, your Majestie hath now in a manner wholly lost, and that wherein a principall part of the honour and safetie of this Kingdom heretofore consisted, in having the absolute com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand <note place="margin">Dunkirk.</note> of the Seas, is so now neglected, that the Town of <hi>Dunkirk</hi> doth so continually beat, rob and spoil your Subjects, that we can assure your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie if some present and effectuall remedie be not forthwith provided, the whole body of this Kingdom, and the shipping and Marriners belonging thereunto, will be meerly lost and consumed.</p>
            <p>The principall cause of which evils and dangers, we conceive to be the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessive <note place="margin">9. Head. Duke of <hi>Buck.</hi>
               </note> power of the Duke of <hi>Buckingham,</hi> and the abuse of that power: and we most humblie submit it to your Majesties most excellent wisdom, whether it can be safe either for you or your Kingdom, that so great power as rests in him both by Sea and Land should be in the hands of any one Subject what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soever. Sure we are, it cannot be for your service, it being impossible for one man to manage so many and so weightie affairs of the Kingdom as he hath undertaken; besides the ordinarie duties of those great Offices which he holds, some of which well performed, would require the time and industrie of the ablest man both for counsell and action that could be found in your whole Kingdom (especially in these times of common danger) And our humble de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire is, that your most excellent Majestie would be pleased to take into consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, whether in respect the same Duke hath so abused his power, it be
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:197877:5"/> safe for your Majestie and your Kingdom, to continue him either in his great Offices of trust, or in his place of neernesse of counsell about your sacred person.</p>
            <p>And thus in all humility ayming at nothing but the honour of Almightie God, the maintenance of his true Religion, the safetie and happinesse of your most excellent Majestie, and the preservation and prosperitie of this Church and Common-wealth; We have endeavoured with faithfull hearts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, and in discharge of the dutie we owe to your Majestie and our Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, to give you a true presentation of our present danger and pressing cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, which we humbly beseech your Majestie graciously to accept, and take the same to heart, accounting the safetie and prosperitie of your people, your greatest happinesse; and their love your richest treasure. A ruefull and lamentable spectacle, we confesse, it must needs be, to behold these ruines in so fair a house; so many diseases, and almost everie one of them deadly, in so strong and well tempored a body (as this Kingdom lately was) yet we will not doubt but that God hath reserved this honour for your Majestie to restore the safetie and happinesse thereof again, as a work worthie so excellent a Prince; For whose long life and true felicitie we daily pray, that your fame and never dying glory may be continued to all succeeding generations.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>